Guide to the Jim Friedman papers, 1962-1965
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Jim Friedman papers 1962-1965
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Friedman, Jim, 1936-
1.5 Linear Feet 9 Items
Economist and Kenan Professor of Economics emeritus at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
Accession (2010-0001) (9 items; 1.5 lin. ft.; dated 1962-1965) consists of research and experiment notes relating to 1960s economics experiments in games and game theory. Also includes Friedman's dissertation, The Theory of Oligopoly.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jim Friedman papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010.
Biographical Note
Jim Friedman is the current William Rand Kenan, Jr. Professor of Economics emeritus at the University of North Carolina in Chapel Hill. He was born in 1936 in Cleveland, Ohio, and earned his B.A. in Economics from the University of Michigan in 1959. He then went to Yale University, where he earned his Ph.D. in Economics in 1963. His dissertation was titled The Theory of Oligopoly.
Following graduation, he was an assistant professor and researcher at the Cowles Foundation for Research in Economics at Yale. In 1968, he moved to the University of Rochester, where he eventually became chair of the Economics Department in 1975. He taught for a short period at Virginia Tech before joining the Economics Department at UNC in 1985.
Friedman's research interests in economics included oligopoly, duopoly, game theory, and noncooperative equilibria. Some of his books include Oligopoly and the Theory of Games (1977), Research in Experimental Economics: An Experiment with Noncooperative Oligopoly (1979, Oligopoly Theory (1983), Game Theory with an Application to Economics (1986), and Problems of Coordination in Economic Activity (1994).
Collection Overview
Accession (2010-0001) includes research notes and results from game theory experiments conducted by Friedman in the 1960s. These are held in hardback folders and sorted by date, beginning with a games experiment in 1962 and ending in 1965. His dissertation, Theory of Oligopoly, is also included. Friedman has also provided his C.V. with some parts circled, reflecting which articles resulted from the experiments present in the collection.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Friedman, Jim, 1936-
Game theory
Economics
Experimental economics
Economics -- experiments
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2010-0001), 1962-1965, (1 box)
  - Friedman's curriculum vitae with circled articles that resulted from the experiments in this collection (Box 1)
  - Games, March-April 1962
  - Price-Profit sheets, 1964 games
  - Games, February 1964 pilot run
  - Games, March 5-6, 1964
  - Games, March 9-10, 1964
  - Games, March 12-13, 1964
  - Price-Profit, 1965
  - November 29-30, 1965
  - December 2-3, 1965